<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercurius Americanus, Mr. Welds his antitype, or, Massachusetts great apologie examined, being observations upon a paper styled, A short story of the rise, reign, and ruine of the Familists, libertines, &amp;c. which infected the churches of New-England, &amp;c. Wherein some parties therein concerned are vindicated, and the truth generally cleared. By John Wheelvvright junior. Philalethes.</title>
            <author>Wheelwright, John, 1594-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E309_37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96300)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E309[37])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercurius Americanus, Mr. Welds his antitype, or, Massachusetts great apologie examined, being observations upon a paper styled, A short story of the rise, reign, and ruine of the Familists, libertines, &amp;c. which infected the churches of New-England, &amp;c. Wherein some parties therein concerned are vindicated, and the truth generally cleared. By John Wheelvvright junior. Philalethes.</title>
                  <author>Wheelwright, John, 1594-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold at the Bull near the Castle-Tavern in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In the title, "Philalethes" is printed in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "A short story of the rise, reign, and ruine of the Antinomians, familists &amp; libertines, that infected the churches of New-England", which is an edition, with added preface, of "Antinomians and familists condemned by the synod of elders in new-England", a work which has been attributed to John Winthrop and to Thomas Weld, who signed the preface.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Winthrop, John, 1588-1649,</term>
               <term>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662,</term>
               <term>Hutchinson, AnneMarbury, 1591-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Familists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antinomians and familists condemned by the synod of elders in new-England.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113316:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113316:1"/>
            <head>TO HIS HONOURED FRIEND Captain THOMAS KINGERBIE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Paper</hi> ſeems to challenge your Acceptance under a twofold reaſon, as it indeavours to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue</hi> your Friend, and as it propounds a <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeas</hi> for your <hi>Tribe;</hi> in all times it is beſt to <hi>dedicate</hi> to a Friend, in theſe times to <hi>a Souldier,</hi> in you I find a concurrence of both: if I look upon you as a <hi>Friend,</hi> you have an <hi>Antitype;</hi> if as a <hi>Souldier,</hi> a <hi>Mercurie:</hi> If you think it not worthy to be <hi>admitted</hi> in the former way, let it be in the latter, and receive it as your <hi>Scout:</hi> If you pleaſe to own it, in either <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or in any <hi>ſenſe,</hi> you reach the expectation, and deſire of your</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>obliged Kinſman, I. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113316:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113316:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THere is a paper lately printed, intituled, <hi>The Riſe, Reign, and Ruine, &amp;c.</hi> upon which I had (in regard of the importunity of ſome friends, together with the expectation of many others, looking at the task as almoſt neceſſarily impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon me) preſumed to obſerve, and indeed I protracted not for want of time; but in hope ſome of the family, or at leaſt, through their direction, ſome of their friends, would have applyed themſelves to it, which when I ſee not, I reſolved upon it (as upon) (in regard of the premiſſes) an Indiſpenſable Act, not out of any affection to be ſeen in Print, but out of a pitie, which I had on Innocence, (unleſſe by this means) reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſly to be oppreſſed under Inſolence and Malice, as appears in the forenamed diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Where we meet firſt with ſome <hi>Apologeticall</hi> paſſages, one of which, is the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a book lately come forth out of the Preſſe, <hi>to which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>he was preſſed by divers;</hi> wherein perhaps he intends, to be <hi>Rhetoricall,</hi> but what is the Reſult of this preſſing, to extract (forſooth) the quinteſſence and ſpirits of the Author: in what? Inperfecting the Hiſtory; which terme perhaps he uſeth ſecretly to excuſe the Incompleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Notions for thoſe things which are perfective, of another eſpecially <hi>per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum formae ſupervenientis materiae,</hi> (Such at his are pretended) uſe to be Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat: But what perfection doth he intend? what degree of <hi>actus perfectivi</hi> will this man give, ſuch as the firſt Act gives? No, thats being, or entity meerly, which it ſeems it had before, or ſuch as the ſecond Act adds, thats a form, formality, this ſurely he would conferre, which he hath done poorly, as appears; or will he go higher, and beſtow the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the third Act upon the ſecond <hi>exiſtence;</hi> and draw it <hi>extra cauſas,</hi> that he hath done, <hi>Extra Ideales ac primordiales</hi> in ſome places, but by this means he hath brought it within the compaſſe, of <hi>hic &amp; nune,</hi> which I am glad of, that I may Anſwer it: But how will he perfect it? He tels us how, by <hi>laying down the ſenſe and order of the ſtory:</hi> What have we here? a <hi>mythologie?</hi> Reall Hiſtories uſe to carry their own ſence, matters of fact need no comment, fictions have their ſenſes, Fables their Morals. Did his zeal of ſending one mite towards the proſtration of theſe Opinioniſts pitch his thoughts, impatient of ſtory, and examining the matter upon gloſſe and invective? or ſhall we conſtrue it as a fatall daſh of his pen, practically pointing out to us the ſequell? Or did the man lay down his own ſenſe, when he reſolved to lay down the ſenſe of the ſtory? Order, perhaps the other uſed <hi>Syntheticall,</hi> and began with Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> whom he cals the <hi>head of the faction,</hi> this man will uſe <hi>Analyticall</hi> and conclude with her; the firſt its likely was ſome ſimple <hi>Theoriſt,</hi> this an Actor in the buſineſſe, I warrant you, let him be what he will, he would ſeem a good <hi>Methodiſt,</hi> not in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall affairs though, for he ſets Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> whom he cals, as before, the <hi>Captain</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113316:3"/> in the rear, which ſeems to be an error unleſſe as afraid of a combat he would put his back into a poſture of retreat, which it may be he intends; and ſo I will follow him. Here is much pretence of conformity to heavens proceedings, whileſt he ſaith, <hi>What God hath pardoned in heaven he would not renew on earth:</hi> But he would be excuſed this correſpondence three wayes. Firſt, by declaring this was in print before he medled with it. But obſerve Reader, he is guilty of the <hi>Order and ſenſe</hi> of it. Secondly, by ſaying <hi>Gods great works muſt be made known:</hi> it ſeems his works mediately by them are greater then his immediate acts. Thirdly, by that ordinary pretence the neceſſity of State, <hi>the times call for his writing,</hi> he ſaith, he would be thought an Oracle of Imperiall depths; A conſiderable penman, upon whom States depend, and whoſe writings the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of Kingdoms expect. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which ſuppoſition I wonder he took no more pains, for he would make us beleeve, he wanted time, which I cannot think, unleſſe by his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>a ſtrait of time,</hi> he mean in alluſion to ſtraits of land, a part of time intercepted twixt two other parts, which might ſo be a yeer, avd is moſt likely: Or unleſſe he mean in regard of the pretended ſeaſonableneſſe of his diſcourſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the opportunity of time; or unleſſe that the matter of his book were ſo blameleſſe as that in charity, we might conceive he did <hi>intueri verbum</hi> when he writ it, and ſo was in a higher meaſure of his Action then time. But whatſoever may be allowed him <hi>in patria,</hi> if that will not be granted him <hi>in via,</hi> if he did make uſe of time, I am ſure he bad a competencie of it at the leaſt, for though he be (I will not detract) one of the higher <hi>ſphaeres,</hi> yet (in which he is higher too) in his diſcourſes, eſpecially polemick, he affects the pace of <hi>Saturne,</hi> under whoſe planetary houre he was born; but if this content him not, but he will (that he may hurry all after his opinion) needs be ſtiled <hi>primum mobile,</hi> let him be ſo; and I in reſpect of, and reverence to his grave, and regular motion will be circumvolved a little with him, onely he muſt give me leave in the nature of an Orbe as well as he, though a lower one, to have a proper motion of mine own, wherein though I thwart him, I may perform my own courſe by which I hope to have ſome influence upon thee unprejudiced &amp; qualified Reader; which obtained makes the period, and revolution of thy <hi>Mercurie,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Wheelwright.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <p>ALthough my Intentions be to apply my thoughts to thoſe things which do expreſly concern Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> yet ſeeing I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to vindicate him, I muſt likewiſe ingage my ſelf in thoſe things which are of remoter and more implicite concernment; wherein he is by way of involution, and as the conſtruction of people ignorant of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may proceed after a more eminent way diſgraced, <hi>viz.</hi> in his being put promiſcuouſly amongſt thoſe whom they call Antinomians, Libertines, &amp;c. and being equally intituled to the erronious poſitions ſubſequent: a groſſe abuſe, not onely to him, but to ſome others, who are brought upon the ſtage,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113316:3"/>that they ſhould be thus indiſcriminately charged as they are in his Preface, which begins thus. <hi>After we had eſcaped the hands of the perſecuting Prelates,</hi> &amp;c. Yes, then you began to be <hi>prelaticall</hi> your ſelves, elſe why did not you admit thoſe men, who left Biſhops as well as ye, to a freedome of ſpirit, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which they came for? or at the leaſt, why did you not protract their cenſures, and give them leave to recover, and recollect themſelves after they were out of the hands of thoſe Prelates? you might have conſider'd, that it was their good opinion of you, and the reformation amongſt you, which ſcrued their meditations in way of preparation for your ſociety, to a ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in doctrine, as well as diſcipline; and there might be ſome diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to errours at the firſt, which would neves have advanced ſo much, had not the <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> of your vehement proſecution forced them into a habit; you might have been pleaſed to have looked at them as men tranſported, through the fancie of practicall liberty to be injoyed, into ſome doctrines of Libertiniſme, and ſo have allowed ſomething to imagination: which is the main, you might haue reviewed your former condition, wherein (as you ſay your ſelves) you were in expoſed to the malice of your <hi>Dioceſans;</hi> divers waies, me thinks, there are whereby you might have taken up your ſelves in more moderate deportment towards your brethren, then in fining, confining, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, disfranchising, baniſhing, and as much as in you lay, killing.</p>
            <p>The infection which the Churches caught by theſe errors ſwels into three heads, <hi>How they have prevailed, how they reigned, and how they were ruined.</hi> Here is their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and here I muſt needs proſecute that which I before named, <hi>viz.</hi> the unequall (and yet too equall) implication of ſome parties, hereafter named in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, all which to my certain knowledge, and, I beleeve, to ſome of theirs even to the <hi>Author</hi> of the book, are diſavow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome of theſe ſuppoſed Libertines, by name, (for ſeeing thſe tenents were attributed to all, yet not <hi>univocally</hi> but <hi>Analogically,</hi> I muſt apply my ſelf <hi>ad principale Analogatum</hi>) Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> who hath openly proteſted againſt them, witneſſe <hi>Mount Wolloſton,</hi> where they know, and our Author tels us, that one of his own Scholars told him, <hi>He ſet up Antichriſt becauſe he did not complie with him;</hi> a heavie charge, which ſurely he would never have put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> to whoſe Doctrine he ever before aſſented, had there been ſo neer an agreement twixt them as this perfecter tels us, whoſe words are theſe, after he had named the opinions of this Scholar of his as he cals him; <hi>Now</hi> (faith he) <hi>theſe things were, ſo groſſe that M</hi> Wheelwright <hi>could not but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them, yet ſo tenderly as ſhewed a near agreement with him in theſe points.</hi> And ſaith moreover, <hi>that they are neceſſarie conſequences which he gathered from his doctrine,</hi> Where there are divers indignities put upon Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> Firſt, that he ſhould large unſound principles. And ſecondly, not know their coniectaries
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113316:4"/>as well as an illiterate man, I can ſcarce for bear to break my order, and fall upon him now, but I ſhall come at length more fitly to it, and ſhall trie how well our Author is skilled in <hi>conſequences:</hi> in the mean time, I uſe this now to let the Reader ſee the injuſtice of this <hi>Medley</hi> of his; if the heat which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires his paper, were true zeal, it would <hi>Congregare hemogenea, &amp; ſegregare he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogenea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are others too as well as Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> who are not affected with theſe paradoxes, as Captain <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill</hi> a gentleman, who did good ſervice againſt the <hi>Pequits,</hi> as it is well known in <hi>New-England,</hi> which their <hi>Emiſſary</hi> might have requited better then to have muſtered him among a troop of <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> under Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> their Captain, as he cals her. Admit he er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet ſhall every little errour touching <hi>Divinity</hi> in militarie men, whoſe ſtirred humours may eaſily attenuate the ſpirits, when they ſo apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and refine them into a <hi>nicety,</hi> be heighten'd into herefie, and preſently ſeen in print? He urged the libertie allowed to Souldiers, inſtanced in the freedome of ſpeech he had to <hi>Count Naſſau.</hi> But my Authors reaſon for ſetting out his book was pretended for his cenſure, <hi>viz.</hi> the neceſſity of State, and ſo the Captain was degraded.</p>
            <p>Another mentioned in his Catalogue is Mr. <hi>Edward Hutchinſon;</hi> I wonder that he is amongſt the crowde, when as he did not uſe to be factious or opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionate. Indeed the <hi>geri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> of that family hath not much inclined to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties, ſcarce any of the <hi>Hutchinſons</hi> have been Sectaries, unleſſe <hi>à latere,</hi> and indirectly, by reaſon of which, me thinks, he might have been placed (if it muſt needs be) more obliquely in this predicament of <hi>Familiſme,</hi> &amp;c. then he is. This man ſaid in the Court (which through Chriſtian libertie he thought he might very well ſay) that If the Court took away his means, he ſhould not be able to maintain his wife and children. Now the Court when they propounded his Fine, might think, (ſuppoſing him to be <hi>Enthuſiaſtique</hi>) that he would not have looked at means as neceſſarie, but rather in a holy triumph have proſtituted all, and expected immediate influence: in which he deceived the awfull and ſerious expectation of the Court, which acceſſary contempt committed him, and re-inforced his prepared cenſures; which might be haſtened the rather by this reaſon too, the Governor comparing the intended Fine with his eſtate, might ſee diſproportion, which he thought might be called <hi>Contempt in Naturalis,</hi> though not <hi>elicitus;</hi> Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they looking at him as apprehenſive of want ſuſpected him; that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit promoted too by a late imagination of the crime, as likely to be ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. However it was, the man was fined fourty pound, and disfranchized.</p>
            <p>Another is Mr <hi>Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hutchinſon</hi> who (as I remember) upon diſlike of ſome proceedings in Court out of a pang of zeal, though otherwiſe no great Crit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113316:4"/>asked a queſtion of them in way of ſeruple, whereupon he was cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red guilty of contempt, and (I think) ſedition too, and ſo was baniſht. But obſerve the wiſdom of the Court, they perceiving, in that he did but meerly ask a queſtion, that there were in him ſome ſparks of truth, and ingenuity, ſent him to a place called, <hi>The Iſle of Errours,</hi> that by the <hi>circumobſiſtence</hi> of corrupt opinions, that little good which he had might be united and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and he at length reduced into an hability of cohabitation; which effect it ſeems it had: for, as I hear ſince, he is reſumed into their precincts. And this I muſt ſay for the Court, they were ſo courteous to him beſides, (rare le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity!) as that they allowed him libertie to come to them to <hi>Boſton</hi> once a moneth, even during his expulſion; I ſuppoſe in the waning of the Moon, when his hotter ſits (as they conceived them) were over, thinking that in ſome competent time, he might be perfectly cured of the <hi>Lunacie,</hi> which they ſuppoſed poſſeſſed him.</p>
            <p>The next are Mr. <hi>Cogſhall,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Aſpinall,</hi> which latter for his diſlike of ſome proceedings of Court was baniſht, and Mr. <hi>Cogſhall</hi> Deputie, preſuming libertie to diſſent from the major part, through reluctation of his conſcience, and reflection upon his priviledge, broke forth into this expreſſion: <hi>That if he could not be heard, he muſt:</hi> whereat he ſtopt, which might have been well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted; for being incenſed by reaſon of the ſevere dealing with his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren before him, <hi>per Imperium voluntatis,</hi> and out of brotherly love, he thought he muſt do ſomething, although his reaſon (for the preſent charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Magick</hi> of the Court ſo powerfully exerciſed upon thoſe that were ſentenced before him) could not tell him what, whereupon he ſtopt at the word <hi>muſt:</hi> for which <hi>apoſiopeſis</hi> he was disfranchized, as one that through ſuch eloquence might become a peſtilent fellow; but ſince he hath lived peaceably, reſolving never to diſcover more <hi>Rhetorick</hi> leſt he ſhould be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p>The next in his book is <hi>Tho: Marſhall,</hi> the Ferrie-man, as he calls him; this good man was occupied in a River called <hi>Charles River,</hi> directly betwixt <hi>Boſton,</hi> the place of theſe Opinioniſts, and <hi>Charles Town,</hi> and other Towns, where his ſpirits being prediſpoſed by the roughneſſe of winds and waves, and agitated by <hi>the Counterbuffes</hi> of Divinitie, which the reſpective paſſengers vented, he might (you will ſay) eaſily be inflamed; Put as long as he kept his watery Element he had an allay: which when he left, and went to the Court, whether he did (as referring to the premiſſes, you may conceive poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) rudely enter into the Court, or whether his feaver beat ſo to his ſingers ends, as it urged him to ſubſcribe to a Petition; however it was, he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced guilty (which indeed is common with watermen) of contempt. Hereupon diſplaced, ſince which time, for want of that imployment, he is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113316:5"/>grown ſo poore, that he will not be able to pay the indiſpenſable halfpeny to <hi>Charon</hi> for his paſſage.</p>
            <p>The next is one <hi>Tho: Grydley, an honeſt poore man,</hi> (as the Pamphleter cals him) yet (as he ſaith) <hi>too buſie in things above his reach;</hi> alas good man he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew that <hi>quae ſupranos nihil adnos,</hi> but the Court cured him of his prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticalneſſe very well; for they took from him his imployment, and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him an abettor of <hi>contempt,</hi> and <hi>ſedition,</hi> which termes he never hearing before, nor not knowing what they might mean, did ſo <hi>amaze,</hi> and <hi>maſquer</hi> him, that ever ſince, in an admiring ſpeculation of, and gazing upon them, he hath ſtood as in a rapture or <hi>extaſie,</hi> not finding leaſure for new action.</p>
            <p>There is one more, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Dyer,</hi> he was charged with contempt too, though I think onely disfranchiſed, that his brain might move in a leſſe compaſſe, whereupon the good man was united into an ability to deliver his mind concerning an opinion of his in the Church, which our <hi>Author</hi> ſaith he did weakly too. In ſuch caſes as theſe me thinks that of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> might have place: <hi>If any one be over-taken with an errour, ye that are ſpirituall reſtore ye ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt amongſt the women is Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon.</hi> This is ſhe who he ſaith <hi>had at once thirty conceptions, ſome bigger, ſome leſſer, ſome of one ſhape, ſome of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and this he aſſures us, ſaying, <hi>That he hath learned otherwiſe (bleſſed be his Name) then to delude the world with untruths.</hi> I queſtion not his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. but I admire his certainty, or rather impudence: did the man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtricate? We know (as he ſaith of himſelf, <hi>he ſometimes hangs up brats againſt the Sun,</hi> but ſurely he medled not with theſe, reſerved I ſuppoſe, &amp;c. unleſſe he had it from him who is ſo <hi>eccentricke</hi> in his motion (as one ſaith of him.) But what if he had it from any then preſent? will that ſuffice to make him ſo confident, as thereupon to take occaſion to ingage, and magnifie Divine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and derive this not known by him to be a truth, from the God of truth? If any of the men he cals Familiſts, &amp;c. had done ſo, would it not have been accounted irreligious? reliſhing of profanenes? &amp;c. would not my Authors ſofteſt expoſition have called it unſavourie?</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Analogy,</hi> which he obſerves betwixt her productions and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>That as ſhe held thirty of the one, ſo ſhe brought forth thirty of the other; Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>fitting thoſe to theſe:</hi> It is a monſtrous conception of his brain, a ſpurious iſſue of his intellect, acted upon by a ſweatiſh and Feaveriſh zeal, which indeed beats almoſt in every line; and reſolves his in themſelves im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſometimes, if not felgned facts into phanatique meditations. For firſt the proportion is not exact, for he reckons not 30. opinions which he cals, Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſons,</hi> and thoſe many of them coincident too, made more I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to prepare for his conceit. Secondly, but admit it were, yet his Notion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113316:5"/>is impertinent, for he brings in defects of Nature, amongſt defects of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. All he can ſay (if he were ſo acute) is, that thoſe are theſe <hi>reductive,</hi> and as they are effects of ſin. A poore plea, by the ſame reaſon he may under the ſame title diſcover all the weakneſſes and naturall imperfections either of man or woman, and fix a kind of morality upon them: But he will ſay perhaps, that this birth was an extraordinary defect: It avails nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he will either raiſe it to a miracle, or at the leaſt prove a ſupernaturall remiſſion of the <hi>formative virtue in her.</hi> That will require a moſt accurate phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall inſpection which I think his learning will not reach, although (for ought I can ſee) his modeſty might: for he tels us of women <hi>purging and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting,</hi> what if the diſtemper we uſually call <hi>Cholera</hi> did for the preſent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thoſe women? muſt it needs be proclaimed? muſt it needs be in print?</p>
            <p>As for Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> ſhe was a woman of a good wit, and not onely ſo, which is all he will allow her, but naturally of a good judgement too, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in her civill occaſions; In ſpirituals indeed ſhe gave her underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over into the power of ſuggeſtion and immediate dictates, by reaſon of which ſhe had many ſtrange fancies, and erroneous tenents poſſeſt her, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially during her confinement, where ſhe might feel ſome effect too from the quality of humors, together with the advantage the devill took of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition attended with melancholy. In a word, as guilty of moſt of theſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and for a pretended revelation of the deſtruction of the <hi>Court,</hi> ſhe was expelled the <hi>Bay of Maſſachuſetts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is Mrs. <hi>Dyer,</hi> the wife of Mr. <hi>Dyer</hi> aforenamed, ſhe was devoted to Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſons</hi> fancies; this is ſhe, who (he ſayes) had the monſter: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the conceptions of her brain had influence upon the conceptions of her wombe, or theſe of the wombe upon thoſe of the brain, I will not diſcuſſe. This <hi>diſcoverer</hi> inclines to the former, I think he might by a deeper ſearch have reached the naturall cauſe whileſt he in his <hi>Method</hi> telling us her pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, judges her for her errours immediately ſentenced from heaven: in which paſſage, as in many other in his book, a ſpirit of cenſure and malice is pregnant.</p>
            <p>The other he ſpeaks of is one good wife <hi>Hunkins,</hi> who, he ſaith, is a <hi>witch;</hi> a poore filly woman, yet having ſo much wit, as perceiving Mrs. <hi>Hutchin:</hi> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of <hi>proſelytes,</hi> to ſupply her wants, ſhe attended on her weekly <hi>Lecture,</hi> (as it is called) where when Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> broached any new doctrine, ſhe would be the firſt would taſte of it: And being demanded whether it were not clear to her, though ſhe underſtood it not, yet would ſay, <hi>Oh yes very clear.</hi> By which means ſhe got, through Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſons</hi> affection to her, ſome good victuals, inſomuch that ſome ſaid ſhe followed Chriſt for <hi>loaves;</hi> Now ſeeing thoſe things were ſo, me thinks our <hi>Author</hi> need not have been ſo rigid
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113316:6"/>in his opinion of her. Alas, <hi>Ars illae ſua cenſus erat,</hi> ſurely a little leſſe gall would (as concerning others, ſo her) have done better in his ink, when, as it appears, ſhe complied with her <hi>patroneſſe,</hi> not ſo much out of love to her <hi>poſitions</hi> as <hi>poſſets,</hi> being guilty I think of no other <hi>ſorcerie,</hi> unleſſe it were conjuring the ſpirit of <hi>Errour</hi> into a <hi>Cordiall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having given you an account of theſe perſons, and paſſages, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Reaſons</hi> which all theſe men might propound to themſelves, for doing and ſaying what they did. Alas, we muſt look at them as men who had left their eſtates, friends, pleaſures of their native ſoyl, ſpirituall <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> extracting the ſweetneſſe of all into freedom of conſcience, doubting not but they might find all in that <hi>Elixar;</hi> but as no <hi>Chymiſt</hi> yet got it, ſo they were many of them deceived; which when they ſurveyed, and ſee the reſult, it might trouble the weaker, and through melancholy fumes diſpoſe them to ſtrange fancies in Divinity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the verdict of the <hi>Court</hi> upon them all, <hi>contempt,</hi> which ſurely muſt proceed from the ſtrong impreſſion that the ſuppoſed contempt of Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> made in the fancie of the <hi>Governor;</hi> by reaſon of which prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion he could conceive no other crime, elſe it cannot but ſeem ſtrange, that there ſhould be ſuch a <hi>ſympathy,</hi> that ſo many men and women too, whoſe ſex may inequalize and difference much, ſhould all run into the ſame <hi>praemwrire,</hi> Such a continuity of ſpirits as this conſent of theirs muſt ſuppoſe, would be a good principle of the Art of the Weapon-ſalve. I give this watch-word to you all, that you are diſgraced <hi>in omni gradu naturae intellectivae ac practicae:</hi> he goes firſt from <hi>practicks,</hi> then to <hi>doctrinals,</hi> then again to <hi>practicks;</hi> thus he runs in a <hi>circle</hi> of abuſe. In the underſtanding he weakens you two wayes, by an inordination of things, and tearms; of things, in the errors; of tearms, in the unſavoury ſpeeches (as he cals them;) in practiſe, by all the poſſible differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of exorbitancie, <hi>pride, boldneſſe, inſolence, deceit, contempt, ſedition, ſchiſme;</hi> all which are indifferently, and indiſtinctly charged upon you in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, ſo that indeed who reads it would think you all equally guilty: and had I any <hi>premiſſes</hi> of the ſame nature, concerning ſome of you, as I have concerning Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> I ſhould vindicate you, as I do him. But ſeeing I have not, I muſt apply my ſelf to him particularly, and free him from thoſe errours and unſavoury ſpeeches, wherein I do but proceed according to the Rule of <hi>Art</hi> which attends <hi>principale analogatum,</hi> which by his own ſaying in his 31. <hi>pag.</hi> is Mr. <hi>Wheelwright;</hi> Now, ſaith he, <hi>all theſe, except Mr.</hi> Wh: <hi>were but young branches,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The way wherby I muſt vindicate Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> is from my Authors own lines in his 42. <hi>page,</hi> where he tels us of the opinions which he (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi>) oppoſed being theſe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113316:6"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That there are immediate revelations without the Word.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That the child of God is dead, not acting at all, but as Chriſt acts in him. Thirdly, that there is no inherent righteouſneſſe in the Saints. Fourthly, that the Commandment is a dead letter.</hi> Now if Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> (as the Author gives us) do abhor theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, let right reaſon, and the ſtrength of <hi>conſequence</hi> judge whether he can be juſtly entituled either to the unſavourie ſpeeches, or to any of the errours; And firſt for the <hi>unſavonry ſpeeches.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> oppugne the opinion of <hi>immediate revelations,</hi> how can he ſay that evidencing juſtification by ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification ſavours of <hi>Rome?</hi> For if he denie immediate, he muſt grant me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate: And that <hi>mediante verbo,</hi> either in an abſolute, (as he grants at the firſt) or in a conditionall promiſe, as he holds at the <hi>ſecond evidence;</hi> And many can witneſſe who have heard him approve evidence of juſtification by ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, but what need of that? doth it not appear in the <hi>principles,</hi> they themſelves do happily give me?</p>
            <p>How can he hold, he is never the worſe for being unholy, nor the better for being holy, when he grants evidence from holineſſe?</p>
            <p>Or how can he ſay, if <hi>Christ</hi> will let me ſin, let him; when as he holds Chriſtians have life in themſelves, a <hi>principle</hi> from which they act. Surely M. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> hath ſo much Logick, as to know <hi>fruſtra fit potentia quae non redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur in actum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or how can he ſay, <hi>I ſeek not grace but Chriſt,</hi> if it be meant in <hi>contempt</hi> of graces? would any man neglect his <hi>evidences?</hi> unleſſe he mean thus? I ſeek not graces <hi>ultimate &amp; reſolutive,</hi> not as the ſupreme but ſubordinate end, not as <hi>principium imperativum,</hi> but <hi>directivum,</hi> not as <hi>quod,</hi> but as <hi>quo,</hi> not to reſt in them, but to move by them to the <hi>place</hi> of reſt: which if he mean, it is not unſavoury, but ſavours of <hi>ſublimated</hi> purity and grace.</p>
            <p>Or how can he ſay, <hi>[I know I am Chriſts, not becauſe I do crucifie the fleſh, but becauſe I do not;]</hi> when he expects teſtimony of ſalvation by ſuch acts of crucifying?</p>
            <p>Or this, <hi>If Chriſt be my ſanctification, what need I look for any thing to evidence my juſtification,</hi> when as it is of the ſame nature with the former, and lies expoſed to the ſame inconſiſtence?</p>
            <p>Now I come to the firſt number of errours, wherein although many things be <hi>coincident</hi> with the former unſavoury ſpeeches, and with the latter num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet I ſhall give you an exact account of the particulars: and as for the firſt of them which is, <hi>That the preaching of the Law is of no uſe to drive a man to Chriſt:</hi> How can he hold it, when as he ſaith, Faith comes by hearing the Word? Now if he allow the Word in <hi>Actu completivo,</hi> in the completure and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a Chriſtians mind, much more in ſome preparatorie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitive acts, as is <hi>drawing to Chriſt;</hi> know, that reaſon gives that a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113316:7"/>to which it will not give a completive power, as to cold in <hi>generation,</hi> as the Philoſophers ſay; ſurely where <hi>completion</hi> is allowed, much more <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or the ſecond, <hi>That a man is united to Chriſt without faith, yea from eternity:</hi> if it be meant reſpecting Gods decree, it is true; but if actually, how can Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> hold it, when as he grants there is ſomething on mans part to receive Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Or the third, viz. <hi>That faith is not a mans receiving of Chriſt, but a mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it:</hi> this is true if <hi>de reflexo actu;</hi> falſe, if <hi>de directo actu:</hi> what matter in this? This is a meer equivocation, you might have ſpared this, but you muſt fill up the <hi>Number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the fourth, <hi>That a man is united to Chriſt without any act of his:</hi> it is the ſame with the ſecond, and may receive the ſame anſwer.</p>
            <p>For the fifth, which is, <hi>That a man hath never effectually Chriſt till he hath aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urance:</hi> it is the ſame with the third, and is true if meant <hi>de certitudine objecti:</hi> but if <hi>ſubjecti,</hi> how can Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hold it, when as he holds the uſe of ſignes, to confirm faith in the regenerate? Which muſt needs allow it ſome latitude, and not limit it to a meer <hi>plerophory;</hi> and ſurely one man never held the fourth opinion and this too; that ſaying, that a man is united to Chriſt without any act of his, this, that a man cannot be Chriſts till he have acted, <hi>viz. reflected;</hi> theſe were not ſo conſiderately jumbled together, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>one factions brood,</hi> as he ſaith. I wonder that having ſuch opportunity to <hi>hang theſe brats up againſt the Sun,</hi> he did not hang theſe further one off the other. For the fixt, which is, that the witnes of the Spirit is meerly immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, without any reſpect to the Word, how can Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hold it when as he oppoſed the opinion of immediate revelation?</p>
            <p>The ſeventh is, <hi>When a man hath the witneſſe of the Spirit he never doubts more:</hi> How can Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hold this if he know what doubt means, being <hi>motus ſuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tramque partem contradictionis:</hi> when as he grants preventives of the motion or deviation betwixt theſe two tearms; in granting confirmation, which is a ſupply of a defect, or an <hi>acceſſary</hi> to a <hi>principall</hi> expoſed to ſome degree of doubt?</p>
            <p>For the ninth, it fals the ſame with this former, and being in the ſame concluſion, onely differenced by a ſuppoſed caſe or occaſion, it will not call for a ſpeciall anſwer.</p>
            <p>The tenth is, <hi>Sanctification can be to evidence of a mans good eſtate;</hi> How can Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hold this when as he oppugnes immediate revelations without the word? Why then he muſt grant mediate; and why may not that word refer to ſanctitie?</p>
            <p>The 12, <hi>viz. No comfort can be lead from any conditionall promiſe:</hi> How can it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113316:7"/>be aſſerted by him, who grants evidence from <hi>Sanctification,</hi> which evidence muſt needs ran in the <hi>Channell</hi> of ſome conditionall promiſe, if not ſo formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet vertually and by way of reſolution.</p>
            <p>The 12. is, <hi>that to ſee I have no grace at all, is true poverty of ſpirit,</hi> and it comes to the ſame with ſome of the former.</p>
            <p>The 13 is, <hi>That the graces of Saints and hypocrites differ not:</hi> How can there be evidence from them unleſſe they <hi>differ?</hi> It may be this is the meaning, they differ not by any poſitiue thing <hi>ſuperadded,</hi> but praeciſely in their owne <hi>Natures,</hi> and are not ſo properly called <hi>different</hi> as <hi>diverſe;</hi> but this is a meere nicetie.</p>
            <p>The 14 <hi>A hypocrite may have</hi> Adams <hi>graces which he had in his innocencie:</hi> it comes to the ſame ſenſe with the former.</p>
            <p>The 15 is this, <hi>All graces are in Chriſt as in the ſubject, and ſo in us as Chriſt is in us, and no otherwaies;</hi> which cannot be attributed to Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> when as he holds (as before we ſaid) evidence from graces, which could not be, unleſſe they were in us, as in the <hi>primary and immediat ſubject;</hi> neither did he ever make Chriſt the <hi>formall principle</hi> of ſuch actions, as beleeving and repenting, which this tenent concludes.</p>
            <p>The 16, which is this, <hi>Chriſt is the new creature;</hi> how can Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> hold it, when he grants evidence from the new creation of graces in us?</p>
            <p>The 17. <hi>God loves a man never the better for being holy, nor the worſe for being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boly:</hi> how can he defend it? who grants manifeſtation of Gods favour in the way of holineſſe?</p>
            <p>The 18. <hi>Sinne in a child of God muſt never trouble bine,</hi> which opinion is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently reducible.</p>
            <p>The 19. is, <hi>Trouble in conſcience for ſinne, ſhewes a man to be under a Covenant of works;</hi> how can he hold it, when as he makes accompt, trouble for ſinne in the Nature of a grace, <hi>proportionally</hi> ſhews a man to be under a Covenant of grace?</p>
            <p>The 20. <hi>A Chriſtian is not bound to the Law:</hi> how can he think it, who expects comfort in a way of ſanctity the <hi>Ectype</hi> of the Law?</p>
            <p>For the 21. <hi>All Covenants made to God in words are Legall;</hi> how can he be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, who holds <hi>Religion and Pietie</hi> requifite in the Saints? which ſurely muſt needs diſcover it ſelf, in ſome godly vowes and reſolutions; unleſſe we will reſtraine it <hi>ad actum primum,</hi> which were abſurd: Perhaps this was in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pofition to Mr. <hi>Wels</hi> his ſtrict Covenant; <hi>never to break Subbath more, never to think idle thought more, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 22. <hi>A Chriſtian is not bound to pray except the Spirit move him;</hi> how can Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> hold it, when (as before) he commits his life to the rectory of the Law, which bids him pray continually? what need he ſtay till the Spirit mover
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113316:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113316:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113316:9"/>any further, when as he grants the Spirit moves only in the word? what need he exſpect the <hi>antecedent</hi> motion of the Spirit, who ſaith, he muſt begin to pray that he may have the <hi>concomitant?</hi> why ſhould he ſuſpend this holy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for an <hi>Imenediate dictate,</hi> when as he grants Chriſtians have a <hi>principle</hi> of life, from which they can act? how can the man ſo ſound in the <hi>premiſſes</hi> think himſelf not bound to pray, but when the Spirit moves him?</p>
            <p>The 23. is this, <hi>A man who hath not this new light, is not able to edifie others who have it:</hi> I ſuppoſe they mean another, <hi>quatenus</hi> another, and ſo the poſition is true <hi>in formali,</hi> for <hi>nil dat quod non habet,</hi> but then, the word <hi>quatenus</hi> muſt be taken <hi>reduplicative,</hi> and not <hi>ſpecificative,</hi> unleſſe by the tear me they attend the <hi>reſpective</hi> entitle, in regard of which it muſt be denyed <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>per ſe</hi> only too, not <hi>per accidens;</hi> in theſe ſenſes, the aſſertion is true: but if we conſider the <hi>materiale,</hi> and ſo they accompt the praecedent errours light, I deny it to be truth, for ſuch light (which I ſhaddow Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> from) is indeed darknes, and tho light which our Author would praeferre to ſhame Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> is very dull, as will appeare; and in the meane time, I muſt apply that ſaying both to this <hi>Opinioniſt,</hi> and to my <hi>Authour, If the light that is in you be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 24. is, <hi>That the whole Letter of the Scripture bolds forth a Covenant of works;</hi> it is true in ſome ſenſe: <hi>xample,</hi> Chriſt bids the young man keep the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements in order to eternall life; This in the letter <hi>pretends</hi> to a Covenant Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, whilſt in its <hi>Anagoge</hi> it intends Chriſt the Authour of ſufficiencie, and ſo pitches upon the Covenant of grace; but that the whole Letter doth ſo, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> aſſertion, when he applies him ſelf to the Law as a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Directory,</hi> which he could not do if he did look at it, as pitching upon a Covenant of works?</p>
            <p>The 25. is this, <hi>No Chriſtian muſt be preſſed to duties of bolineſſe,</hi> which in regard of the good expected by Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> from holines, cannot be his doctrine.</p>
            <p>The 26. <hi>No Chriſtian muſt be exhorted to Faith, Love, &amp;c.</hi> admits the ſame anſwer.</p>
            <p>The 27. is, <hi>A Man may have all graces and yet want Chriſt;</hi> Indeed he may have repreſentations of them, graces <hi>aequivoce,</hi> but not true graces; and if true, not as <hi>Synonymous</hi> to ſaving, but as oppoſed to fained; but in the evill ſenſe, how can Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> hold it, when as he <hi>attributes</hi> unto graces, power to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence Chriſt?</p>
            <p>The 28. is, <hi>A beleivers Activity is only to act to ſinne;</hi> This pofition implies Chriſt the <hi>formall principle</hi> of vertuous Acts; which conceit wee before excuſed Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> from. Indeed, how can it be aſcribed to him who (as our Authour tels us) oppoſed this tenent (viz.) that a Chriſtian is, <hi>(that is his phraſe)</hi> a dead lump not acting at all?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113316:9"/>
            <p>Thus I have runne through the <hi>unſavory ſpeeches,</hi> and the firſt ſcroule of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; I come to the other ſcroule, being 82. Why might not all theſe poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been put in one <hi>Number,</hi> as well as in ſo many? I ſhould think, were he not a <hi>New-Englandman,</hi> that he intended ſome myſtery in the <hi>Number of</hi> 3, which he ſo oft prefers, firſt in his <hi>Title, Riſe, Raigne, Ruin, Familiſts, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, Antinomians, cenſures of Church, proceedings of Court, Judgments of heaven upon them,</hi> and here <hi>with his three parcels;</hi> but ſurely the good man is no <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goriſt,</hi> but a <hi>Platoniſt</hi> rather, which his ſeparato <hi>Ideae,</hi> contempt, and ſedition, not properties of the men to whom he attributes them, <hi>Chimeraes</hi> only of his reſtleſſe braine, declare him; but howſoever if he did purpoſe a <hi>Numerary ſpell,</hi> ſeeing thereby he doth many times repeate, I ſhall conjure him downe with meere Figures ſomtimes: my meaning is, that in regard of the <hi>recidence,</hi> not in ſenſe only, but words many of them into the former, I would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed though I do not give you a Particular accompt, as before, for although our <hi>Authour</hi> hath laviſhly <hi>tautologized,</hi> which perhaps may be Natural to him, and ſo ſcarce admit a <hi>Criticiſme,</hi> yet I will not trace him, unwilling to oppreſſe the <hi>Reader,</hi> and draw my ſelfe into the ſame height of babling; Nor let any think I hereby ſeek eluſion, <hi>verbum ſat ſapienti,</hi> let ſuch examine.</p>
            <p>For the firſt ten they are eafily reducible.</p>
            <p>The 11. is, <hi>As Chriſt was once made fleſh, ſo is he in us ere we be carried to perfection;</hi> This propoſition, as many other we ſhall meet withall, is wrapt in ſuch myſlicall terms, as it ſcarce falls under the common rules of conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if this tenet intends <hi>Hypoſtaticallunion,</hi> how can Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> approve it, when as by the Authours confeſſion he oppoſed that Doctrine which ſayes; <hi>Beleivers act not at all, but Chriſt acts in them, and doth</hi> (as before named) <hi>formally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive and formally repent,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> could not rationally contradict, if he patronized this notion; which being granted, a believer ſhould not <hi>proximately</hi> believe and repent, but Chriſt muſt obtaine <hi>rationem formalis principii</hi> in him.</p>
            <p>For the 12 13.14.15.16. to the 24. they are in the <hi>categorie</hi> of thoſe before pretermitted, as reducible to the former.</p>
            <p>The 24. is this, <hi>That he who hath the Seale of the Spirit may judge of an elect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> According to this Aſſertion, one Seale muſt at once make two <hi>Characters:</hi> which opinion I muſt tel mine Author plainly, his principles, and his parties, rather lead to then Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> for a <hi>reſpective impreſſion,</hi> in order to graces inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, (ſuch as theirs is pretended) may in al reaſon ſooner by the ſame virtue wherby it ſhews to one his own Election, ſhow to him the Election of another in whom the ſame perfections may be apparent, then an <hi>Irreſpective &amp; abſolute impreſſion,</hi> ſuch as Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> is accounted, as will be ſeene in their opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning evidence of ſalvation; however, how can Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> own this, unleſſe he either think Gods eternall Decree attendeth ſome quality, the <hi>Symbolical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of which might direct him in his cenſure? or unleſſe he hold Immediate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113316:10"/>revelations without the Word, within it there being no ſuch <hi>pertintous?</hi> Or unleſſe he preſume to look in <hi>ſpecula Trinitatis?</hi> Which Mr. <hi>Welds</hi> ſeems to do, whileſt he tels us <hi>what God bath pardoned in heaven,</hi> and to <hi>whom he purpoſes his immediate</hi> puniſhments on earth.</p>
            <p>By our Reaſon <hi>of caincidence</hi> we paſſe to the 28, which is the firſt we can find challenging a particular anſwer, and that ſcarcely too; it is this: <hi>To af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, there muſt be faith on mans part, to receive Chriſt, it to undermine Chriſt:</hi> this is nothing, but an <hi>efflux</hi> of the formen fancie of <hi>hypoſtatioall</hi> union; the uſe of faith is to apprehend Chriſt <hi>ſub eonceptu formali:</hi> the effect of which is a <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> union, not at all in that which may be more <hi>phyſically</hi> looked at, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>hypoſtaticall:</hi> The next conſiderable is the 33, which is this, <hi>To act by vertue of a command is legall.</hi> This is Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> which taken <hi>cum grano ſalis,</hi> will be ſavoury enough. Let us know to act legally may be taken two wayes: <hi>Vel non atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo principium effecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um action is, vel formale ſivè exemplare.</hi> In the firſt Reaſon, they act legally who think to do things in their own ſtrength <hi>formally.</hi> In the ſecond, they act legally who think to do ſo <hi>conſtructive,</hi> and by way of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, ſuch as the <hi>Goſpels young man,</hi> who did fulfill the Commandments <hi>ſub ratione particulari,</hi> In which act he expected vertue from Chriſt, and ſo in the firſt ſenſe acted not legally. But he did not, <hi>ſub ratiane magis univerſali, &amp; eminentiori,</hi> and therefore he acted legally in my ſecond ſenſe. In his <hi>Acoeſſe</hi> to the Law under its <hi>typicall</hi> and immediate pretence, was his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in his <hi>receſſe</hi> from it under its <hi>reflexive intention,</hi> and true Evangelicall <hi>Tropologie</hi> was his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. To act <hi>legally</hi> is to recede from the virtue, by which one is to act; which virtue of Chriſt is <hi>vel Chriſti tanquam officientis, vel tanquant Ideae.</hi> To act by vertue of a command, that is immediately from it, is, <hi>Vel immediatione virtueis, vel ſuppoſiti:</hi> they who act by ſtrength of a command in this firſt ſenſe, attend not Chriſt either in the reaſon of an <hi>efficient</hi> or <hi>Ideae,</hi> and ſo muſt needs act legally both wayes. For the command hath a twofold <hi>habitude, directive</hi> and <hi>objective,</hi> he who acts immediately from the <hi>directive</hi> order of the Law, acts legally, <hi>non attingendo Chriſtum ut Ideam:</hi> he who acts immediately from the <hi>objective,</hi> acts legally, <hi>Non attingendo Chriſtum, ut efficientem.</hi> And thus its true, to act by virtue of a command is legall; but if it be meant <hi>immediatione ſuppoſiti</hi> (not that I think a command hath properly <hi>ſuppoſitalitie,</hi> but onely <hi>aliquid Analog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn,</hi> which reaches my notion and intent) it is not true, that to act by virtue of a command is legall.</p>
            <p>The next conſiderable is the 41. which is this: <hi>There be diſtinct ſeaſons of the workings of the perſons in the ſacred Trinity, ſo that a man may be ſaid to be thus long under the work of the Father, and thus long under the work of the Son, and thus long under the work of the holy Ghost.</hi> If by this, we are ſo long under the Father, he intended onely an excluſion of the Son in ſome <hi>eminence,</hi> and degree of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113316:10"/>It is not againſt that <hi>received maxime, Opera Trinitatis ad extra ſunt indiviſa:</hi> and the generall opinion of Divines excuſes it from a <hi>paradox;</hi> For what more common then to attribute redemption to the Son? conſolation to the holy Ghoſt? What more uſuall then to ſay, the Father humbles, the Son raiſes up, the holy Ghoſt comforts? Touching which, I thus conceive: that the very ſame <hi>individed eſſence</hi> as it doth put on divers reaſons or <hi>notions</hi> (as the Schoolmen ſpeak) is ſaid to perform divers actions not by a <hi>ſimple excluſion</hi> of the <hi>Attributes</hi> of any of them in this or that Act, but onely <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid, Notionally,</hi> as we may conceive, according to the common <hi>quidditie.</hi> The Father is in himſelf, and ſo produces a Son of comfort, by reflection, he loves that iſſue, and ſo educeth illumination; in this ſenſe, <hi>Opera ad extra ſunt diviſa,</hi> for from the diviſion <hi>ad intra,</hi> why may there not follow a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall diviſion <hi>ad extra</hi> too? ſeeing the relations of thoſe divided acts are reall, and <hi>extra intellectum,</hi> which would otherwiſe plead Reaſon for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation; I ſay why may they not have ſome effect upon the acts <hi>ad extra</hi> too? and make them in ſome ſenſe <hi>diviſa?</hi> And if it be improper to ſay, <hi>Deus eſt trium perſonarum,</hi> but onely <hi>eſſentia eſt trium, &amp;c.</hi> why may there not be ſome impropriety to ſay (I mean in oppoſition to the above-named Doctrine) that, <hi>Deus eſt trium Actuam</hi> reſpectively, when as theſe acts do in the common opinion attend thoſe <hi>relations?</hi> But if an abſolute and ſimple diviſion be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> cannot hold it; when (as it is very abſurd in it ſelf, ſo) his doctrine <hi>of evidence by ſanctification,</hi> where there muſt be Chriſts <hi>attractive,</hi> and the Spirits <hi>illuminative</hi> power, and of ſignes which require a concurrence, proclaims.</p>
            <p>The next is this, <hi>Conditionall promiſes are legall:</hi> If it be meant that they are in a legall form, its true, whether <hi>cauſaliter</hi> or <hi>conſequative;</hi> But if it be meant that they are legall <hi>virtually,</hi> and ſo not to be made uſe of in the time of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> how can Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hold it, when as he grants evidence from graces, conditionall promiſes being the <hi>current</hi> wherein ſuch evidences paſſe?</p>
            <p>The next conſiderable is this: to <hi>lay the Brethren under a covenant of works hurts not at all, but tends to much good.</hi> What did I ſay conſiderable? a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtrangely produced as it were in an indifference twixt truth and errour: if it be preſented as an errour, we muſt needs by reaſon of the indefinitenes of the phraſe ſuppoſe all Brethren to be under <hi>a covenane of grace.</hi> If it be a truth, what doth it among errours? to make even number? What ſhall we ſay? its neither true nor falſe, but ſtands in a pure preciſion; he imagined though perhaps that the confinity of errours (wherein obſerve how his malice mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplies hereſies upon them) would determine its <hi>neutrality,</hi> and hereupon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages at once all his <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> to effect an abſtraction which he might
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113316:11"/>have reſerved till an exigence, and in the mean while have referred this <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to the unſavoury ſpeeches with which it moſt <hi>ſymbolizes.</hi> But he was afraid, leſt it ſo eaſily ſeaſonable either way, ſhould have ſeaſoned them, which he prefers to diſreliſh the appetite of the <hi>Reader,</hi> to the parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in his Narration. But he ſaith, if it be good to lay the Brethren under a Covenant of works, then it is good to bite one another: which argument is much like one of his brats he hangs up againſt the Sun.</p>
            <p>The next is this: <hi>Faith juſtifies an unbeleever.</hi> If the ſenſe be, that the faith ſubjected in Chriſt juſtifies me in whom there is not any, its falſe: if you take it in <hi>ſenſu compoſito,</hi> it is ſo, if <hi>in diviſo,</hi> its true. I wonder ſuch grave diſcurſiſts (as my Author by his ſtyle ſeems) ſhould with theſe poore ſubtilties put us upon ſuch <hi>elementary diſtinctions,</hi> in reſolving which <hi>Simths</hi> Logick will claim a principall ſhare. But perhaps he did it to evade a more ſolid reply, thinking no <hi>Eagle</hi> would catch ſuch flyes. Which way of his is in the mean time my advantage, whileſt by medling only in my <hi>ſphere</hi> I cannot be ſaid to preſume, which incourages me yet to tell him that this opinion is a <hi>conſectarie</hi> of theirs, who deny graces in the Saints, not of Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> doctrine who grants them.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Aſſertions are either coincident, or ſuch as concern Church Diſcipline, wherein diſagreement is not pretended.</p>
            <p>Thus we have done with his <hi>pretended errours.</hi> Now we come to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Crimes, <hi>viz. contempt and ſedition;</hi> which the Court pickt out of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of his, he preached upon a Faſt-day deſigned for peace, the ſubſtance whereof was this: Chriſts abſence is a main cauſe of faſting, therfore labour for him revealed in the Covenant of grace; peace is to be ſought in ſuch a drawing neer the <hi>God of peace;</hi> and oppoſe thoſe by contending for the faith, but ſpiritually, who go the way of the Covenant of works (as in that thing) (wherein indeed they are oppoſite to the end of the day) as enemies to grace, and in that reſpect perſecuters of Chriſt, as (which word I ſuppoſe is, <hi>ſieut qualitatis</hi> onely) <hi>Herod, Pilus,</hi> and the <hi>Jews.</hi> This is the <hi>doctrine</hi> wherein the ſpirit of <hi>ſedition and contempt</hi> breathes according to their opinion; I will therefore briefly leaving the fuller diſcuſſion to <hi>Statiſts,</hi> (by ſome of which Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> hath been already cleared,) examine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contemptus eſt ex hoc quod aliquis rennit ſubjici legi bonae;</hi> conferre, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates publiſh a Faſt in order to peace, whether this publication have the compleat Nature of a Law, let others determine. But admit, Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> whileſt he tels them, peace is the moſt eaſily attainable in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to whom they muſt apply themſelves in a Covenant of grace, twharts not their Law, unleſſe it had expreſſed the method which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt uſe, or unleſſe Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113316:11"/>had done that, the contrary of which it did neceſſarily imply; But there is no ſuch matter, for in his generall terme, a <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> he could not be inordinate, but admit <hi>explication,</hi> though it might render ſuſpition of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe in doctrine; yet not ſuſpition, much leſſe apparency of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to civill diſcipline, therefore what neglect of Authority was here, when neither the expreſſion nor conſtructive intention of their Mandate was croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Or, if it had been, yet not the primary end, and ſo could not conſtitute ſuch an offence: As for <hi>finis operantis,</hi> the ends they themſelves reſerved, how could he attend? unleſſe we either ſuppoſe a <hi>coincidence,</hi> or unleſſe they think it requiſite, Clergie-men ſhould ſtudy <hi>Myſteries of State,</hi> or unleſſe (which they ſeem to abhor) he ſhould have expected immediate revelation of them? <hi>[Renuit] he will not;</hi> that preſuppoſes admonition, and ſuppoſes contumacie, Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> had no ſuch preparatories; If he had reiterated the diſcourſe, though innocent, there had been more <hi>pretence.</hi> But grant further he had, yet a meer repetition makes not frequency; But admit, yet <hi>frequentia peccati non facit peccatum ex contemptu, ſed diſponit ad hoc:</hi> according to <hi>Aquinas.</hi> It is far then from contempt, which is not ſo much as a bare diſpoſition towards it? what if he did (this as a ſuppoſition, onely) decline the next purpoſe of the day? yet if he did reach it more eminently by ſetting up <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he told them was the cauſe of faſting, muſt he have theſe crimes attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to him, becauſe he did ſo conciſely compleat their deſires? might they not have taken up themſelves twixt his ſuppoſed <hi>receſſe,</hi> and <hi>relapſe</hi> before they proceeded to cenſure? But our Author ſaith, (<hi>pag.</hi> 52. wherein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends aggravation) <hi>whereas Mr.</hi> Cotton <hi>urged peace, Mr.</hi> Wh: <hi>contention in the afternoon:</hi> Yes, but it was ſpirituall, and for a Covenant of grace too: the way of peace, as in that generality, cannot be denyed. The ſpirits of men in Winter (as it was then) have too much aſperity in the morning to be truſted with <hi>zealotiſmes,</hi> which in the afternoon their more mollified diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions may admit: but <hi>more ſeriouſly:</hi> what would this man have by this <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance?</hi> where is the ſence of it? or how aggravates it? would he have had Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Text to have been impoſed by the Court? were not that to limit the Spirit? or would he have had him betwixt forenoon and evening Exerciſe, not being half an houres ſpace, by reaſon of the <hi>directive</hi> Sermon, to have pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſied his meditations into ſuch a <hi>complexion?</hi> Or would he have had him ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was no time, to change his <hi>text,</hi> or his <hi>Notions,</hi> to have defiſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>paroxyſme?</hi> Alas! ſo the Church as well as the State might have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended contempt. Or if he had in ſuch an Auditory adventured upon an extemporarie diſcourſe, would not your Moderatſts conſtruction have pitched upon <hi>neglect?</hi> But what need of all this? Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> and <hi>He</hi> agreed in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113316:12"/>the main, both their labours directed to the ſame ſcope, (<hi>viz.</hi> to bring men to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the difference of <hi>preciſion,</hi> and degrees of heat allowed: ſo that if his Sermon offered violence to the day, yet where is that which is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>State?</hi> Admit <hi>incongruity,</hi> yet where is the <hi>contempt?</hi> If it had been any thing, it had rather been <hi>indiſcretion</hi> then contempt; and rather <hi>indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> then indiſcretion.</p>
            <p>But they ſay, <hi>By thoſe under a covenant of works, he meant them, ſome Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and ſome Miniſters; and that he knew they went the way which he deſcribed to be a covenant of works.</hi> Admit, yet his expreſſions from the Pulpit in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Rules of conſtruction can have no ſuch reference: Or ſuppoſe they might have reference, yet not of <hi>cauſality</hi> but <hi>connexion</hi> onely, which would give no advantage to <hi>ſecular</hi> power, or <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> either. But further, grant a reference of <hi>cauſality,</hi> that may be concerned in the Authority of the <hi>keyes,</hi> not of the <hi>Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He inſtances in that difference of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts, ſub una &amp; ſub utra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> as a paralell caſe; but it is not, for thoſe tearms did denote upon the free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the right of their reſpective attributions: it is not ſo in this matter, where the phraſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Covenant of works,</hi> is not confeſſed by the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> &amp;c. as their condition; therefore to ſay under a <hi>convenant of works,</hi> and under a <hi>covenant of grace,</hi> is not as much as to ſay, <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>ſome others,</hi> there being much diſtance twixt this occaſion and the former.</p>
            <p>He would at length puzzle the people with ſubtilties, whil'ſt he talks of deſignation to common intendments, ſaying, <hi>That which deſigns a man to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intendments doth as much as if it ſhould name the men;</hi> Which phraſe if apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed muſt preſume, that the Magiſtrats and Miniſters he pleads for, are by that member of the diviſion <hi>under a Covenant of works:</hi> commonly intended, A pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty peece of work, wherin to give you his upſhot, firſt he contradicts himſelf, ſecondly, totally excuſes Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> thirdly, he accuſes his own partie more then ever any did. A brave Champion, firſt he contradicts himſelf in ſaying, <hi>theſe things were never heard of before</hi> Mr. <hi>Wh. came into the Courtry;</hi> p. 24. wheras it ſeems it was <hi>vox pepuli</hi> before, for he was then but newly arrived, and this the firſt time he thewed himſelf in that publick way.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he excuſeth Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> for when to ſtopp his mouth, we had halfe allowed him <hi>indiſcretion</hi> in that Sermon of Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> yet he will needs cleere him from it by implying that through the common rumour of <hi>Magiſtrates &amp;c.</hi> walking the way of the Covenant of works, there might be occaſion miniſtred unto him, and need for ſuch a diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he accuſerh both the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> more then any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113316:12"/>yet did, by intimating a precedent continued, and manifeſt addiction of theirs to <hi>Legaliſme,</hi> whil'ſt he declares them commonly intended by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>under a Covenant of works.</hi> and by the generall opinion of the people wrapt in it.</p>
            <p>This was a great overſight, unleſſe by a check of his conſcience ſuggeſting Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> innocencie, he was moved to vindicate him ſecretly from crime, and therefore would <hi>myſtically</hi> do it in the word <hi>Intendment,</hi> to purge his heart from malignity of opinion.</p>
            <p>And whereas he ſaith, p. 25. <hi>The former Magiſtrates and Miniſters had great diſreſpect after</hi> Mr. <hi>Wh. his Sermon,</hi> which he ſaith, was the cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Firſt, It is not known that ever they had any notable neglect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Admit, yet his inference may intitle the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to ſedition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The inequality of obſervance did not proceed from any effect Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> Sermon had upon them; as in that inſtance of the <hi>Halberds,</hi> the former Governor having more carried before him then his <hi>ſucceſſour;</hi> and in the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions againſt the <hi>Pequeds,</hi> but from the affection which ſome deſigned to thoſe offices, bore to the then Governor Sr. <hi>He: Vain,</hi> who by his noble, affable and diſcret carriage, ingaged their utmoſt attendance; where obſerve the edge of Malice, which when it dare not ſuppreſſed by fear, openly, yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly it will fix, though he do not inroll Sr. <hi>Henry</hi> amongſt Familiſts, &amp;c. Though he will not ſay, he was ſuch a <hi>Sectary,</hi> yet whilſt he talks of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment above the following <hi>Governor,</hi> as an Iſſue of Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Sermon, upon his own <hi>premiſſes,</hi> he neceſſarily inferrs it.</p>
            <p>And wheras he ſaith, <hi>That before Mr.</hi> Wh. <hi>came over, all things were peaceable, after his arrivall, nothing but diviſion.</hi> I anſwer: Firſt, he <hi>contradicts</hi> himſelf, for he tels us Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> vented her Opinions in the ſhip as ſhe came over, <hi>pa.</hi> 31. he tels us, ſhe drew many to her, <hi>pa.</hi> 32. he tels us, ſhe procured coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from eminent perſons, <hi>pa.</hi> 33. hence (ſaith he) <hi>was the trouble to the Paſtor of Boſton,</hi> &amp;c. hence, ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Wh: took courage to inveigh in his Sermon,</hi> &amp;c. It ſeems then there was Diviſions before Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Sermon, and that it was an effect of them rather then a cauſe. Secondly, there was a company in the <hi>Bay</hi> before he came, who upon ſuppoſition of 2 parties, one under the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works,</hi> the other themſelves under the <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> had reſolved upon ſchiſme, expecting onely a beck from the Pulpit; which when by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> naming a <hi>Covenant</hi> of works and of <hi>grace,</hi> (though not with any ſuch <hi>pertinence,</hi> their prepared <hi>phanſies,</hi> thought they had) they took this <hi>Idoll</hi> of their own brains, for a <hi>providence</hi> of heaven, and hereupon ſacrificed their <hi>premeditated</hi> endeavours to it; as it had been the <hi>Image</hi> which fell down from <hi>Jupiter;</hi> which <hi>doing</hi> of theirs Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> was not acceſſary to, their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113316:13"/>Covenant of <hi>grace</hi> being <hi>compoſed of errours,</hi> his covenant of <hi>grace</hi> which to decline <hi>legaliſme</hi> he preferred, being free from them, carrying along with it the <hi>grace of the covenant.</hi> He tels us, <hi>pa.</hi> 26. of a writing which much concerned Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> to read, that might be; it may be it was our <hi>Authors,</hi> for all his (as he ſaith of his book) are neceſſary for <hi>States,</hi> much more for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>perſons:</hi> but it ſeems Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> was ſo dull as not to conceive the <hi>neceſſity,</hi> for <hi>he did not read it, as we are told;</hi> what then? perhaps he was otherwiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; But what ſaies the man? <hi>Which did argue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the height and pride of his ſpirit:</hi> what need theſe ſynonyma? were not pride enough? this argues my Authors malice and virulencie; but is he not aſhamed to talk ſtill of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, when his <hi>Independent</hi> brain hath bewrayed ſuch inconſequence? Let him never think hereafter with any <hi>judicious</hi> Reader to be reputed for a <hi>ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt:</hi> but if he think he ſhall hide his talent unleſſe he imploy the Preſſe, let him rather (as one ſaid) <hi>write meer hiſtory, and ſuch too where in partiall reſpects may not byaſſe him to errour.</hi> Which way (as though he preſaged diſlike of his <hi>controverſall</hi> diſcourſes) he hath already taken in his <hi>book,</hi> now at the Preſſe, called, <hi>A Narration of the proctiſe of N. E.</hi> wherein he may do (as in things that fall under his <hi>ſenſe</hi>) much better, then in <hi>polemicall</hi> Eſſayes, where he doth but <hi>loſe</hi> himſelf, and <hi>over-ballace</hi> his muddy <hi>intellectuals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay ſo vaſt is my <hi>Author</hi> in his apprehenſion of pernicious effects from Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Sermon, that he would make people beleeve, it not onely moved all Societies on the Land, but that it had its influence upon <hi>veſſels</hi> at Sea <hi>(thats his phraſe) How, ſaith he, did it hinder all affairs in Courts, in Towns, in Families, in veſſels at Sea? pa.</hi> 58. As though it had been like <hi>that commotion of the earth lately there, which Ships at a great diſtance felt;</hi> as though Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> had made an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> amongſt them. Whereas (which I hope the Reader will conceive) it was nothing but a <hi>Trepidation</hi> of the <hi>ſpheres</hi> in that New <hi>Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Another pretended crime of his, is <hi>ſedition,</hi> which is thus defined: <hi>Seditio eſt praeparatio ad impugnationem corporalem;</hi> A preparation to a bodily fight: now how did Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Sermon prepare for ſuch a fight? He bids them indeed in the Apoſtles expreſſion <hi>contend for the faith,</hi> &amp;c. but he deſignes (as before we ſhewed) no parties. Or if he had, it was to a ſpirituall <hi>conflict,</hi> as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd himſelf, which reſpects not civill unity, or <hi>unitatem-Juris,</hi> as <hi>ſedition</hi> doth, but <hi>Eccleſiaſtique;</hi> and ſo at the moſt it could be but <hi>ſchiſme;</hi> and not that neither, unleſſe his doctrine be proved <hi>contra utilitatem,</hi> and ſo be errour. Nay, that is not enough neither, unleſſe it were in <hi>fundamentals,</hi> and ſo might be called <hi>hereſie;</hi> for <hi>ſchiſma</hi> alwayes <hi>ſibi aliquam confingat haereſin, ſchiſme</hi> is ever attended with <hi>hereſie,</hi> in the opinion of the learned: nor is all this ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to bring it under the cenſure of the Church it ſelf, unleſſe it be <hi>per ſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113316:13"/>intentum:</hi> for that which is <hi>per aceidens,</hi> no more in <hi>morals</hi> then in <hi>Naturals,</hi> can conſtitute a <hi>ſpecies,</hi> ſuch as <hi>ſacred</hi> Authority muſt proceed upon; as I ſaid before of <hi>contempt,</hi> ſo of this, if it had been any thing it had rather been <hi>faction</hi> then <hi>ſedition,</hi> and rather <hi>ſchiſme</hi> then <hi>faction.</hi> Before my <hi>Author</hi> propound his reaſons wherby he would faſten theſe <hi>crimes</hi> upon Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> he wiſely premiſes thus; ſaith he, <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>Such as would receive ſatisfaction may, if they will read that which follows, &amp;c. carrying this along with them, that the acts, &amp;c.</hi> He ſaith true in this, ſuch as come prejudicate and preſuming neceſſity of juſtice from <hi>N. E.</hi> may ſatisfie themſelves in his <hi>Apology;</hi> but as for others, let them attend his deſcriptions, and it will appear they do as little fit Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> practice as his <hi>examples. Seditioſus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>eſt qui facit diſſenſionem animorum:</hi> good in it ſelf, but applyed <hi>rudiori Minerva,</hi> if it be taken rightly, <hi>viz.</hi> Diſſention <hi>in ordine ad civilem unitatem:</hi> leſt <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>ſchiſme</hi> be confounded, and the word <hi>facit</hi> be ſo qualified as to exclude <hi>accidentall, occaſionall,</hi> and <hi>periſiaticall</hi> action upon mens minds, it concerns not Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> caſe, it being neceſſary too, (which I may adde) that it be not onely <hi>motu praevio,</hi> but <hi>concomitativo,</hi> which is moſt intrinſick, and of the formal reaſon of <hi>velleitie</hi> which muſt be ſuppoſed at the leaſt in ſuch a crime, his other deſcriptions, <hi>cum ſaevit populus, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>cum eunt alii in aliud,</hi> call for the ſame reſtrictions, and refer to the firſt.</p>
            <p>He exemplifies to as little purpoſe, as in <hi>Demetrius</hi> his ſedition, and <hi>Corah</hi> with his complices: this is much like his <hi>ſub una &amp; ſub utraque,</hi> as little para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell where he intends, <hi>Demetrius</hi> named the man, <hi>This Paul, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo did <hi>Korah</hi> particularize, Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> nothing ſo, he onely ſpake in <hi>theſi, the Hypotheſis</hi> was their own, the application was theirs: My <hi>Author</hi> cannot make it appear their caſes are alike, unleſſe he reſume his ſublime Notion of <hi>Deſigniation to common intendments,</hi> &amp;c. by which he might ſalve the <hi>Phaenomena;</hi> but we have tried that before.</p>
            <p>That which he ſaith, <hi>viz.</hi> my <hi>Author,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Wh: vehemencie of ſpirit, and voyce in proclaiming them perſecuters, and Antichriſtian, who walk the way of a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works,</hi> it muſt be reckoned amongſt his <hi>impertinences,</hi> ſeeing <hi>the degree doth not vary the kind;</hi> let him be as urgent as he pleaſeth. <hi>Salvaratione fidei, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va ſpecie,</hi> whileſt he keeps within that <hi>univerſality</hi> againſt thoſe which are <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galiſts</hi> which he did and onely did, let me uſe my <hi>Authors</hi> main Argument, which we meet with preſently. Put the caſe in a <hi>Reverſed Frame,</hi> if my <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> had flamed in <hi>zeal</hi> never ſo much againſt Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> Sermon, or ſome of the Opinioniſts, would he have admitted that as a <hi>topicke</hi> of Sedition? In ſuch a <hi>particularization</hi> which is more then he can fix upon Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> would not the equity of his cauſe have been his <hi>plea?</hi> Doth he not therefore rove a little in this diſcourſe? if <hi>vehemencie of ſpirit and voice</hi> infer <hi>ſedition,</hi> it will be dangerous
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113316:14"/>to have good <hi>Lungs;</hi> let my <hi>Author</hi> take heed he intrench not upon his <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity tenure,</hi> and inſcribe that to <hi>crime</hi> which intitles him to the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> his vehemencie made him not <hi>exorbitant,</hi> he miſt not the <hi>cuſhiou,</hi> nor was he ſo fierce as my <hi>Author</hi> was when he ſaid, <hi>Lye with him Devill, ſleep with him Devill, &amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> promoted a <hi>Covenant of grace</hi> by a ſpirituall <hi>proſtration</hi> of its oppoſites. And this in generall too, this is all he did: what, Pretenders to ſo much charitie, Reformation, Chriſtian liberty? &amp;c. A new Heaven and a new Earth (as ſome ſaid of them) and ſo, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>celeſtiall,</hi> arraign, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, impriſon, baniſh a man of their <hi>Church</hi> too? And as though this were not enough, <hi>Inſtare morienti</hi> to fame him an <hi>Heretique, Antinomian,</hi> ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, what not? and this in print, with all poſſible diſgrace and <hi>diminution;</hi> and that after he had repented too (as is confeſſed) one upon whom he ſaith he would not reflect any thing, his meaning is, I ſuppoſe, that the rayes of his malice ſhould fall directly upon Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> and all this for ſo ſmall a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? <hi>Tanta fallacia?</hi> &amp;c. May I not retort, <hi>Tantaene animis coeleſtibus irae?</hi> His fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe is a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> which he by his uſuall clapping together of Scriptures magnifies the more, becauſe he conceives it wanting in Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> But how comes it in here under his title, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Proof of Sedition</hi> and <hi>contempt?</hi> ſurely he doth not think that indiſcretion involveth contempt. What doth this curious Impertinent mean? I ſhould think that there were a ſecret and <hi>energeticall ſubſidence</hi> of all into this vice, and that in his opinion too, if he had not (as we before ſhewed) cleared Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> from ſuch offence. See how confuſed the man is, he would convict him of contempt, and yet vindicates him from indiſcretion, as though that could be without this, what he means by diſcretion I know not. But. if it be that which is uſually called ſpirituall diſcerning, my <hi>Author</hi> did uſe to annex it to the <hi>tribe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>His laſt and main ſtratagem whereby he will prevail upon the moſt preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, and ſcrupulous <hi>ſpirits,</hi> is to put the caſe (as he ſaith) in a <hi>reverſed frame,</hi> his words are theſe: <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>But if any ſhall yet pretend want of ſatisfaction, &amp;c. put the caſe in a reverſed frame if ſome others had taught it, &amp;c. would not Mr.</hi> Wh: <hi>and, &amp;c. have looked at themſelves as intended? Yes ſurely, for a proper adjunct may deſigne a particular company, as well as names, as</hi> Judas <hi>by the ſop.</hi> This is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent deviſe: A conjecture what Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> and the other partie would have ſaid upon the like invective: I know not what they would have ſaid, &amp;c. nor do I know what to ſay to this his maſter-peece of putting the caſe, &amp;c. unleſſe I ſhould put it into the caſe. <hi>Quid dignum tanto? &amp;c.</hi> Shall we neglect it? No, <hi>the neceſſity of the times may call for it,</hi> it is the very diſtilled quinteſſence of his brain, his Catholicon. We will (if we can) ſqueeze ſome ſenſe out of it, or at the leaſt leave it in a capacitie; if it have any force for the preſent, we muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113316:14"/>poſe our <hi>Author</hi> knows, <hi>per ſpecies concreat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> But I <hi>would not reflect upon him,</hi> (as he of Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi>) as though he had no more wit then he was born with: But what if he knew what they would ſay, ſhall their practiſe, or ſpeech, which may (as they are men) proceed from <hi>paſſion</hi> direct yours? If they ſhould take offence at a little <hi>forwardneſſe, freeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>irreſpectiveneſſe</hi> of diſcourſe, and beat it out as you have done into <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>contempt,</hi> ſhall that be your <hi>Apologie?</hi> Are a company of <hi>Familiſts, Libertines,</hi> &amp;c. ſo <hi>authentick?</hi> If it muſt be ſo, let Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> or ſome others ſend word what they would ſay,<note place="margin">So a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and this great oration of my <hi>Authors,</hi> even <hi>tota haec Româ ruit cum viribus ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s:</hi> of all his <hi>coixcidences, impertinences, foleciſmes,</hi> fruitleſſe and weak <hi>chullitions,</hi> this is the worſt, for thoſe may be acted upon, and refined by wit. But as for this, it may ſtand eternally before it can receive a good <hi>conſtruction,</hi> all the colour, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of reaſon it can admit, muſt be expected in a meſſage from <hi>New England,</hi> declaring what they would ſay, &amp;c. My <hi>Author</hi> might do well, <hi>to compaſſe Seato make a Proſelite,</hi> to go himſelf thither and procure an <hi>expreſſe,</hi> but I doubt he will not, his mind doth ſo run <hi>upon the ſop:</hi> where I leave him; And in the mean time I leave this high ſtrain of his, if the winds and ſeas favour in a poſſibilitie of being cloathed with a little kind of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or the beſt kind of <hi>non-ſenſe:</hi> Alas! poore <hi>argument.</hi> The caſe in a <hi>reverſed Frame</hi> might better have been kept in the caſe then dut into the Frame.</p>
            <p>He concludes this diſcourſe thus; <hi>That to lay thoſe under a Covenant of works, who have ſuffered as much as himſelf, ſavours not of a brotherly ſpirit,</hi> p. 58. This can be looked at no otherwayes then as an impertinence too, if the Apoſtle ſpeak truth: If I give my body to be burnt, &amp;c. I do not ingage my ſelf in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, &amp;c. onely I ſay <hi>utcunque</hi> his concluſion is not concluſive: <hi>he makes had premiſes, and worſe concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing theſe things are ſo, that there is ſo little ground for theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>crimes,</hi> ſeeing there can be no contempt found in Mr. <hi>Wh: Sermon,</hi> we will rather impute the undeſerved <hi>cenſures</hi> to ſome other cauſe then to the meet malice of the <hi>Court,</hi> which ſome uncharitably do.</p>
            <p>Whether it were a ſtrong <hi>imagination</hi> of the then <hi>Deputy</hi> upon Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> which by the power annexed to <hi>phanſie</hi> produced ſome contemptuous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in him while he was before them?</p>
            <p>Or whether it were that he, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Deputy,</hi> being then occaſionally in contemplation of <hi>contempt,</hi> and preſuming of the infallibility of his <hi>ſcience,</hi> being (as he thought it) not <hi>ſimplicis intelligentiae</hi> (which is more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) but <hi>viſionis,</hi> which in that reaſon muſt have <hi>aliquid externum de facto</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of it, thereupon pitched on <hi>contempt,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> delinquencie.</p>
            <p>Or whether it were (which is <hi>probable,</hi> in the deſpicableneſſe of the <hi>State,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113316:15"/>and eſpecially of the then <hi>Deputie,</hi> late <hi>Governor,</hi> and in regard of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, and that deſervedly) to that worthy gentleman then <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> Sir <hi>Hen: Vain,</hi> unlikely to return into that <hi>preferment</hi> ſpeedily; I ſay, whether in regard of his condition, his <hi>melancholy temper,</hi> ſeconded, as obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by a <hi>ſullen conſtellation</hi> then predominant, he did abſolutely determine he was <hi>contemned,</hi> ſome way, or other, and ſo <hi>cum nemini obtrudi potuit,</hi> he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it upon Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> And ſo <hi>ſedition,</hi> by way of <hi>concomitance; Sedition</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt being twins,</hi> as he uſed to ſay; howſoever Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> was ſentenced guilty of the <hi>faults,</hi> and thereupon <hi>baniſht, impriſoned</hi> firſt: upon requeſt indeed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed to his <hi>family,</hi> not to ſtay though above <hi>twelve</hi> dayes upon pain of ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>cenſure,</hi> although in a <hi>remote place,</hi> where they could not fear any <hi>effect</hi> from the <hi>pretended vices, &amp;c.</hi> And although in ſo <hi>cold</hi> a <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of the yeer, wherein I think, had he had the very <hi>extracted ſpirits</hi> of <hi>ſedition,</hi> and <hi>contempt,</hi> they would have been <hi>frozen</hi> up, and indiſpoſd for <hi>Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſaith my <hi>Author,</hi> p. 43. <hi>it pleaſed the Lord to hear his poore people, whoſe ſouls had wept in ſecret, for the reproach, &amp;c.</hi> I deſire to know of Mr. <hi>Welds</hi> what he means by <hi>pleaſing</hi> of the Lord? whether <hi>ratione voluntatis Determinantis, vel determinatae?</hi> In the mean while, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge whether he have not cauſe to weep not onely in <hi>ſecret,</hi> but <hi>openly</hi> for the <hi>reproaches</hi> which he hath caſt upon ſome. He goes on thus: <hi>It is the Lords doings, and it is marvellous in our eyes. Mr.</hi> Wh. <hi>is gone to Paſcal,</hi> &amp;c. what then? it was neither <hi>contrà,</hi> nor <hi>praeter,</hi> nor <hi>ſuprà naturam,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Wh:</hi> to go to <hi>Paſcal:</hi> where is the <hi>wonder?</hi> I confeſſe it was <hi>marvellous</hi> he got thither at that <hi>time,</hi> when <hi>they expelled</hi> him, by reaſon of the <hi>deep ſnow</hi> in which he might have <hi>periſhed.</hi> Whether my <hi>Author</hi> profane not <hi>Scripture</hi> in this, I will refer it to thoſe whom in the ſame <hi>page</hi> he ſpeaks of, <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>dear and beloved Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
